{"tossups": [{"question": "One faction of fans of this sport supposedly promoted the heresy of Monophysitism, opposing pro-Orthodoxy fans. Supporters of this sport burned half of Constantinople during the reign of Justinian the Great in the Nika Revolt. The richest athlete in this sport, Gaius Appuleius Diocles, competed for the Reds using a<em> quadriga</em>. For ten points, name this sport held in the Byzantine Hippodrome and the Roman Circus Maximus, a highly dangerous vehicular race.", "answer": "<b> chariot racing</b> (\u201drace\u201d not needed after mentioned; prompt on \u201cracing\u201d before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This woman convened the first meeting of the Ninety-Nines. This woman\u2019s spouse debunked baseless rumors that this person was secretly Tokyo Rose. Will Rogers facetiously coined the term \u201cPowder Puff Derby\u201d to describe a race where this pilot took third. The USGS<em> Itasca</em> failed to locate this person after she didn\u2019t check-in with Howland Island. Fred Noonan disappeared with, for ten points, what American aviator, the first woman to fly solo across the Atlantic Ocean?", "answer": "Amelia<b> Earhart</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "With the help of Cossack K.S. Leontiev, this kingdom\u2019s military modernized in the 1890s and entered a dispute with a European power over the wording of the Treaty of Wuchale. This country, which was once controlled by the communist Derg regime, fought a 17-year civil war that ended in 1991 with it losing its access to the Red Sea. Eritrea broke away from, for ten points, what East African country that is also blocked from the sea by Djibouti and Somalia?", "answer": "<b> Ethiopia</b> (accept<b> Abyssinia</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "The South African Police Service murdered 17 strikers who extracted this commodity in the Marikana Massacre. Great Zimbabwe merchants often traded this commodity for porcelain and silk with the Sultanate of Kilwa. A colony named for this commodity first fell to a European power after multiple Anglo-Ashanti Wars. For ten points, name this commodity that, along with salt, was the primary trade good of medieval and early modern West Africa.", "answer": "<b> gold</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A story about this man claims he was impersonated by his wife Pompeia Plotina. During the reign of this man, Lusius Quietus ended the Kitos revolt. This man commissioned Apollodorus of Damascus to create a bridge over the Danube. This man\u2019s victory at Tapae, and thus his conquest of Dacia, are commemorated in a spiral bas relief located upon a namesake column in the Forum. For ten points, name this second of the Five Good Emperors.", "answer": "<b> Trajan</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This Regionalist work was inspired by the artist\u2019s visit to the town of Eldon, Iowa and titled for a style of architecture that appears in the farmhouse in the background. The central figures in this painting were modeled by the artist\u2019s dentist and sister, who was irritated when this painting was originally exhibited as \u201can Iowa farmer and his wife.\u201d For ten points, name this Grant Wood double portrait of a stoic pitchfork-holding farmer and his unamused daughter.", "answer": "<b> American Gothic</b> BONUS:<em> American Gothic</em> was awarded third prize in a competition held by this midwestern city\u2019s Art Institute, which then purchased the painting for its collection. ANSWER: (Art Institute of)<b> Chicago</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Martin Garcia Onez de Loyola led an expedition to capture the last emperor of these people, Tupac Amaru. Legendarily, a ruler of this empire came out of Pacaritambo holding a golden staff after being birthed from the divine pairing of Mama Killa and Inti. This empire that used the knot system of<em> quipu</em> experienced a civil war between Huascar and Atahualpa. For ten points, name this South American empire conquered by the conquistador Francisco Pizarro.", "answer": "<b> Inca</b>n Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "When syncretized with the Egyptian god Amun, this Roman deity was depicted with ram horns. The Flamen Dialis was the high priest of this deity, who formed the Archaic Triad with Quirinus and Mars. In the<em> Metamorphoses</em>, this deity transforms into an eagle to kidnap the Phrygian prince Ganymede; in the form of a bull, this god kidnapped Europa. This son of Saturn was the husband of Juno and the father of Minerva. For ten points, name this chief Roman god, the Roman equivalent of Zeus.", "answer": "<b> Jupiter</b> (accept<b> Jove</b>; do not accept or prompt on \u201cZeus\u201d)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "This country\u2019s constitution, the Henrician Articles, defined the rights of its elected kings. The Union of Krewo was a precursor to this country created when a Jagiellon ascended the throne. In this country, any member of its legislature could veto a bill through<em> Liberum veto</em>. Prussia, Austria, and Russia partitioned this country three times. The Union of Lublin created, for ten points, what country governed from Krakow and Vilnius?", "answer": "<b> Poland</b>-Lithuania (or the<b> Polish</b>-Lithuanian<b> Commonwealth</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Private landlords in this country controversially maintained control over two-thirds of their land following an 1861 emancipation reform. This country was the home of the People\u2019s (+) Will, a revolutionary group that, in 1881, assassinated the leader of this country. This country ended its institution of (*)</b> serfdom in the aftermath of its loss in the Crimean War. For ten points, name this country where Tsar Alexander II was assassinated in St. Petersburg.", "answer": "<b> Russia</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "</b> <b>An armed insurrection in this city during (*)</b> World War I led to the death of sixty rebels in the Easter Rising. For ten points, name this headquarters of the political party Sinn Fein [shin fayn], the capital of Ireland.", "answer": "<b> Dublin</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker! (1) <b>Thousands of residents of this state threatened to invade Canada to free John</b> <b>Gilfillan, Loren Fletcher, and Eugene Wilson, who had been arrested after attempting to kidnap conman Lord Gordon Gordon. John (+) Rockefeller operated the Franklin Iron Mine Company in this state to exploit the Mesabi Range. In the Election of (*)</b> 1984, this was the only state won by Walter Mondale. For ten points, name this state where Hubert Humphrey failed to become mayor of Minneapolis. ANSWER:<b> Minnesota</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}